拉斯·冯·提尔
《女性瘾者》
斯特兰·斯卡斯加德 (Seligman)
你如何看待Seligman？
在我来看他是一个缺乏生活经验的人
I made him a man who had very little experience of life...
他的经验都来自于阅读
through experience and only through reading.
他试图用他极其有限的想象力去…
And who tried to use whatever limited imagination he had to...
理解现实和生活 然而…
to understand reality and life, but...
生活难以从书本上学会
It's very hard to learn about life from books.
因为…生活太复杂了…
Because it's... so complicated, so...
充满矛盾…
full of contradictions and...
很难…缩减成…格言警句
It's very hard to... reduce to... intelligent sentences, life.
所以才有了艺术
That's why we have art.
才有了像拉斯这样的电影
That's why we have films like Lars's then.
拉斯的电影 正如所有电影
And Lars's film are like all films...
最佳状态 不是电影明确了什么
They're not best when they're pinpointing something...
或告诉你一些很具体的东西
or telling you something very concrete.
最好的是…看起来模糊 开放又怪异的时候
They're at their best when they're ambiguous, and open, and strange.
Seligman如何令Joe愿意向他倾诉？
他比较友善
Well he's nicer.
她觉得安心
She feels safe.
如果想让别人向你倾诉一生
I mean if you want to hear somebody tell about their life...
你得让对方感觉安全 知道你感兴趣
they should feel safe, and they should feel that you're interested in them.
但我不觉得他是蓄意为之
But I don't think he's calculated that much from his side
因为他并不善于社交
Because I think he's not socially skilled or...
也不善于利用别人
Or really good at manipulating people, because of his...
如我所言 他缺乏实际的生活经验
As I said before, lack of real life experience
但他也是…将影片引向那些题外话的关键因素
But he's also... a crucial instrument for the digressions in the film
是他岔出去 谈论假蝇飞钓
Because he takes off talking about flyfishing or ...
谈论圣像画…
how icons are made or ...
诸如此类 是他扰乱了她的故事
staff like that. So he's responsible for fucking up her stories well.
但是她理解 她处理好了
But she get it. She gets it up. It's ...
这部电影的形式基本就是…
The form of the film that... it is basically...
两个人在房间里坐了5个小时
It is two people sitting in a room, for 5 hours.
一直聊天 还有些片段
talking. But with flashes of...
闪回 切换到其他场景
backflashes and... cuts of... other locations as well
夹杂着拉斯以他独有的幽默 用画面语言做出的评论
and mixed up with Lars's very humoristic way of making his own comments visually
等等…但这是种不常见的形式
and everything. But it's a form that you usually don't see.
多半电影学院也不会赞同
and that they probably wouldn't recommend in film school.
你和拉斯·冯·提尔关系如何？
首先我很喜欢他 我们是好朋友
First of all, I love him. We're very good friends.
和他一起拍摄很有趣
We have a lot of fun when we're working.
甚至…我不觉得是在工作
and I don't even... It doesn't feel like work to me.
感觉就像在把玩素材 看看其中的可能性
because it feels like you start playing with materials. See what can be in it.
作为演员 没什么职责规定
And you have no responsibility, as an actor.
你不是来完成什么特定的任务
You don't have to come and deliver something specific.
因为…和拉斯拍戏就是一个探索的过程
Because... the process of shooting with Lars is the process of discovering.
这样很好
which is very nice.
另外 欺负他很好玩
And then, it's fun to humiliate him and...
他欺负我也是…
get humiliated by him and...
之类的 我们俩非常合拍
sort of them. The tones between us are very nice.
主要是…我就是喜欢和他一起
But basically... I just love being with him.
冯提尔的导演风格这些年有何转变？
我是从他放弃了完全的导演控制权之后…
I worked with him with his first featured film…
破浪 (1996)
拍的第一部长片开始和他合作的
after he gave up total control.
影像多面体(1982)、犯罪元素(1984)、瘟疫(1987)、美狄亚(1988)、欧洲特快车(1991)
他的前五部电影是完全由自己掌控的
His first 5 featured films were totally controlled.
演员每个动作 所有一切 都是他设计好的
He designed every movement of the actors and everything. And they were...
技巧卓越…
technically brilliant and he...
但他最终熄了火
and off course dead.
在电影节看到他首部片《犯罪分子》时 我说…
When I saw his first film Element of Crime in a festival, I said...
要是哪天这个导演对人有兴趣了 我想和他合作
"I'd like to work with this director when he gets interested in people."
花了几年时间 后来他自己意识到了
And it took him some years. But then he realized himself. And he...
《医院风云》里 他有点打破了这种全面控制
With The Kingdom he sort of broke up this total control thing, and realized that he...
意识到他可以…在银幕上展现出真实的生命
could actually have... get real life on the screen...
只要他放手让演员去演
if he let the actors go.
我们拍《破浪》时 剧本非常详尽
And when we did Breaking the Waves, which was... very thought-out script.
我称其为 情节剧里的《夺宝奇兵》
I called it the Raiders of the Lost Ark in terms of melodrama.
因为每个场景都像是情节剧里的高潮
Because every scene was like the peaks in a melodramatic film.
如果他不给演员更多自由 去演活
If he hadn't let the actors be more free, and create more life...
你就会察觉出编排的痕迹
you would have felt the structure of it...
也就不会有这么好的效果
and then it wouldn't have worked this well.
他这些年一直在摆脱自己的工具
And he was... he spent all those years taking away his own tools...
他的 “道格玛95宣言” 是关于…
He... the Dogma Manifesto, it‘s all about...
是非常私人的
it's very personal thing.
不是规定电影该如何拍摄的纲领
It's not a manifesto "This is the way films should be made".
是关于他自己摆脱工具 一路缩减
It's about him taking away his own tools, and reducing everything to...
最终走到了《狗镇》
eventually gets down to... all the way to Dogville, which is...
只有文本 和演员 就他妈开拍了
just a text, an actor, and fucking shoot it.
他就是这么做的
And it's what he did. And...
我们拍《狗镇》时…
When we did Dogville, you...
你会发现故事本身足够强烈 因此可行
You see that the story itself is so strong, that it actually works.
再由演员 来注入生命力
And then you have actors that... bring life to it, and not...
不是试图表现演技 只是演活剧本而已
not trying to do great performances, just to bring life to it.
再拍出来
And then you photograph it.
就足够了
And it works.
这些年他一直在弱化使用的工具
So he has been reducing his tools throughout the years, and then...
而最近他又重拾他的技巧…
Lately he has started using his knowledge again...
用所谓更传统的拍摄方式
of sort of more traditional film making.
拍出了《忧郁症》这样优美的电影
And made a beautiful film like Meloncholia.
这部片中我们甚至没用手持摄影
And on this film we didn't even have hand-held camera, we had...
我们用了三脚架和导轨 在他而言非常少见
Tripod and tracking, which was very exotic.
他也一直在调整自己的拍摄方式
So he's constantly moving around in his ways of working as well...
不仅为了找到适合每个故事的表达手法
to find not only the ultimate way to work for each story...
也是为了发展自己的方法
but also to develop his own means.
如他所坚持的那样放弃了他的工具之后
After having given up all his tools as insisting...
我是说 当然仍是他在主导
I mean, he's still in control off course...
因为是他在做剪辑
because he's doing the editing.
已经摆脱工具多年之后 现在他又重拾了回来
But after giving away his tools for many years, he's now bringing them back in.
但不会再约束演员了
but now without constraining the actors.
这样很好
which is great.
你会怎样形容提尔的电影？
它们都不尽相同 不是吗
Well they are all different, aren't they?
它们在风格上差异很大…
They are so different in style and in...
共同之处是…
What they all have in common is that...
它们都以…拉斯的笔触作为基础
They have Lars's way of... Lars's writing is in the bottom.
这是拉斯电影的标志
And that is how you recognize a Lars's film.
对白总像是…
The dialogue is always like...
有点像 小孩在喋喋不休…
It's a bit like child talking away, he writes...
我有次跟他说 我读你的剧本时 想到的是…
I told him once that, "When I read your scripts, I think of a...
一个极为聪明 但是稍微有点变态的小孩…
a highly intelligent but slightly pervert little child that is...
坐在玩偶屋旁边 一个个剪下玩偶脑袋
sitting with a doll's house and snipping the heads of the dolls."
他说 是吗
And he said, "Yes?"
你会想到这一幕是因为…
And you have that film because it's...
这就是为什么很难在他的电影中自由发挥
That's why it's so hard to improvise in his films.
他想让演员自由发挥 但这种对白很难发挥
He wants you to improvise, but you can't improvise that kind of dialogue, because...
其中有种天真 通常有种童话的腔调
There's a naivete to it. There's a fairy tale tone to it usually.
有这样的特质
That has a certain quality.
他所有电影都有这种非写实的笔触
So... all his films have that tone that is not realistic.
但电影的风格各异…
Then they are in style very different, from...
《忧郁症》可以说是他比较浪漫的电影
Say that Meloncholia is one of the more romantic films he's made.
《白痴》可以说是他比较生猛的电影
You can say that The Idiots is one of the rawer films he'd made.
这部戏可以说是…
You can say that this film is...
他所有想法的集合
everything that he comes up with in his mind.
就像他直接在用脑子在画布上涂抹
It's like he's painting the canvas with his brain.
无论什么联想和看法 他都直接扔了进来
Whatever associations he has and ideas he has, he just throw in there.
这是个有趣的过程
It's an interesting journey.
这部戏中的性爱是如何处理的？
How is sex used in the film?
首先 当你看到画面极尽色情有何感觉
First of all, what would you feel when you see it is that pornographic?
性爱就成了种人类活动 牵涉不常暴露的身体器官
It is human behavior, with body parts that you usually don't see ... exposed.
就变得…不性感了 只是普通的动作
And it becomes... not sexy, becomes normal behavior.
这是种有趣的效果 这很好
And that is an interesting effect of it, which is very good.
手法不是那么风雅
The art is not artsy-fartsy...
但当然整部电影…
but off course the entire film is...
作品整体 被提升到了一定艺术水准
and the universe of the film, it's elevated to an art level.
因为展现出了不常见的视角 不寻常的人物
Because it's not our everyday world that we see, the everyday character that we see.
但是 在银幕上看到阴茎送入阴道的画面
But it shouldn't be strange to see a dick enter a cunt on film...
不该比看到勺子把粥送进嘴巴 感觉更怪异
than it is to see a spoon enter a mouth with porridge.
应该如何理解这些性爱场面？
这是拉斯对一个有性瘾的女人的想象
It's Lars's fantasy about a woman with nymphomania.
而且一如往常 这是个虚构的故事
And it's as always a story. It's fiction.
但是是基于一种非常残酷的现实之上
But it's based on a very inhuman reality.
但我也觉得…
But I also think it's...
也是拉斯的一种沮丧 对于这个充满禁忌的世界
It's Lars's frustration with the world, where there are too many taboos.
人们对他人的越轨太少宽容
where there's too little tolerance in terms of accepting people's deviations
在性事或任何方面
in sexual behavior or whatever.
我个人认为…
My personal idea is...
只要两个人自己愿意 不论他们做什么都可以
if two people enjoy it, then it's fine whatever they do.
只要没有人是受迫 去做自己不想做的事
as long as nobody is sort of forced into something that they don not appreciate.
我们应该谨慎干预他人的性生活
We should be very careful in designing other people's sex life.
你会觉得该片存在争议吗？
Do you find the film controversial?
片中的性爱 对我来说毫无争议
To me the sexuality of the film is not controversial at all.
但我猜在阿富汗就不一样了 或者在盐湖城
But I bet it is in Kabul, or Salt Lake City.
因此这取决于观者
So it depends on who we are.
对我而言…
To me...
裸露和性爱只是些身体的功能而已…
nudity and sexuality is just some body functions...
我没有宗教的恫吓
I don't have the curse of religion...
某些身体器官是禁忌之类的
that sort of banned certain body parts.
拉斯·冯·提尔
《女性瘾者》